4KTY字幕作品.致敬经典系列
适配 GBR英版蓝光.汤臣版配音LPCM2.0音轨
Rev.20230921.01
4KTY字幕作品.致敬经典系列
适配 GBR英版蓝光
Rev.20230920.01
片名：霸王别姬
Farewell.My.Concubine.1993.GBR
一九七七年·中国北京
1977 BEIJING, CHINA
一九二四年·北平·北洋政府时代
1924 - PEKING - THE WARLORD ERA
一九三七年·“七·七”事变前夕
1937 - ON THE EVE OF WAR WITH JAPAN
一九四五年·日本投降
1945 - THE JAPANESE SURRENDER
一九四八年·国民政府离开大陆之前
1948 - BEFORE THE EVACUATION OF THE KMT TO TAIWAN
一九四九年·人民解放军进入北平
1949 - ENTRY OF THE PEOPLE'S LIBERATION ARMY INTO PEKING
一九六六年·北京·“文革”前夕
1966 - START OF THE CULTURAL REVOLUTION
革命文化 对于人民大众
THE CULTURAL REVOLUTION IS A POWERFUL WEAPON...
是革命的有力武器
IN THE HANDS OF THE PEOPLE'S CONGRESS."
十一年后
ELEVEN YEARS LATER, 1977.
一九九〇年，在北京举行了 [纪念京剧徽班
进京二百周年]的庆祝演出活动……
A celebration performance was held in Beijing in 1990
to commemorate the bicentenary anniversary of Anhui opera.
干什么的
Who are you?
噢
Oh,
诶 京剧院来走台的
We're with the opera troupe.
哎哟 是您二位啊
Oh, I didn't recognise you!
啊
What?
啊 呵呵
Ah, Yes.
我是您二位的戏迷
I'm a great fan of you both.
是啊 哎呦 呵
Is that so?
您二位 有二十多年 没挨一块儿唱了吧
It's over twenty years since you've performed together, isn't it?
噢 差不二十...有 啊
Oh, almost twenty...
二十一年了
Twenty-one.
二十二年
- Twenty-two.
啊 对
Yes,
二十二年了
Yes, twenty-two years.
诶 我们哥俩 也...也有十年没见面了
And it's been ten since we last saw each other.
十一年
Eleven. Eleven years.
- 啊... 是 是 啊 - 十一年
- That's right,  - eleven years.
是十一年 是
eleven years, yes.
都是“四人帮”闹的 明白
I see, it's the fault of the Gang of Four.
可不 都是“四人帮”闹的
Isn't everything?
现在好了
Things are better now.
可不
That's for sure.
现在好了
Everything's fine now.
呵呵 是…是
Yes, yes.
您二位 在这儿等一会儿
Please wait here a moment.
我去给您开灯去啊
I'll go and turn on the lights.
哦 呵呵 您受累 嘿嘿
Oh, Sorry to put you to so much trouble.
哟 这不是艳红吗
Hey, Yanhong, is that you?
这老没见了 你可想死我啰
It's been ages. I've been missing you badly.
臭婊子 你
Slut!
各位爷
Ladies and gentlemen,
多捧场了啊
the show is about to begin!
各位爷
Ladies and gentlemen,
好
Great!
小癞子又跑了
Laizi is running away again.
好小子 我看你往哪儿跑
Brat! See how far you get.
去给我追回来
Quick, go catch him!
各位各位
Gentlemen,
啊 包涵着点啊
please be patient.
哎呀 爷儿们 爷儿们
Sir, sir,
诶 您高抬贵手
Sir, sir, do forgive us.
什么下三滥的玩意儿 也敢到这儿露脸
Trash! How dare you show your goddamn faces around here?
爹
Dad.
我操你们大爷
Fuck you all!
各位爷都站好了甭动 真钱买真货
Don't anyone move. You'll get your money's worth!
我小石头今儿玩真的
Just as sure as my name is Shitou,
让爷爷们开开眼
I'll give you something to look at.
- 师哥 - 好
- Bro. - Great!
唉哟
Ah me.
嚷嚷什么啊
What are you screaming for?
我还没招呼呢
I haven't even said hello yet!
你个狗屁的大师兄
You're a bulishit artist.
你他妈连个猴儿都演不了
You can't even play a goddamn monkey.
你日后怎么做人呢 你
What are you going to do with your life?
别当你今天的 玩了个邪 拍了个砖
You thought you'd get away with that brick act,
你以为 我饶了你啊
did you?
那是下三滥的玩艺儿
It's garbage.
我叫你们干啥的啊
I told you to run, didn't I?
跑
Run!
跑 跑
镪菜刀
Sharpen your knives!
磨剪子来
Bring your knives for sharpening!
镪菜刀
Sharpen your knives!
您这孩子啊
This child...
没吃戏饭的命 您带回去吧
...isn't fated to be an actor. Take him home.
您想啊
Think of it,
他这一亮相
When he made his debut on stage,
- 那台底下听戏的人 不都吓跑了 - 磨剪子来
- he'd scare off the audience! - Sharpen...
镪菜刀
...your knives!
不是养活不起
It's not that I can't afford to raise him,
实在是男孩大了 留不住
but he's getting too big
这才来投奔您来了
...to keep at the brothel.
您老好歹得收下他
Help me. Please take him.
您只要收下他
If only you'll take him,
怎么着都成
you can do anything you like.
您别嫌弃我们
Don't look down on us.
诶 别介
How could I?
都是下九流 谁嫌弃谁呀
How could I? We're all equally despised by society.
他祖师爷不赏饭吃
But if there's no job for him,
谁也没辙
what can I do?
起
Stand up.
娘 手冷
Ma, my hands are cold.
水都冻冰了
The water's all turned to ice!
娘
Ma!
哪儿来的窑子里的 一边去
Get away from us, you son of a whore!
窑子里的东西 掉地上喽
It's from the whorehouse! Drop it on the floor!
我冷啊
I'm so cold.
- 诶 真着了耶 - 真着了
- Hey, Ah, it's really on fire! - Yes.
快...快
Hurry.
我冷死啦
It's freezing!
你们是不是欺负他来着
Are you bullying him?
过来 跟我睡吧
Come over here. Sleep with me!
呵呵
Ha-ha.
够横的啊 你
You're really something!
- 小癞子 - 诶
- Laizi, - Yes.
- 睡和尚被窝里去 - 啊
- go snuggle up with the Little Monk. - Right.
嘿 接着
Hey, Catch!
外面冷极啦
It's so cold outside!
小爷我撒的尿在牛那眼上 可就结成冰溜子了
My piss froze on the tip of my dick.
差点没顶我一跟头
I nearly turned a somersault!
凡是人的 就得听戏
If you belong to the human race, you go to the opera.
不听戏的 他就不是人
If you don't go to the opera, you're not a human being.
什么猪啊 狗啊 它就不听戏
Pigs and dogs don't listen to opera.
是人吗
And are they human?
它畜牲
They're beasts!
所以呀 有戏就有咱梨园行
And where there's opera, there's work for us actors!
- 别嚷嚷 别嚷嚷 我不爱听  - 我不
- Stop squealing! - I'm not!
收
Abdomen in!
立腰
Straighten that back!
若想人前显贵 您必得人后受罪
If you think you're above everyone else, you'll learn the hard way.
今儿个是破题 文章还在后头呢
This is just the beginning, wait till you see what's in store!
小豆娃 没事儿
Don't worry, Douzi.
朕都耗了一炷香了
They burned a whole stick of incense before I quit.
豆子 忍着点
Just keep at it.
- 小石头 - 诶
- Shitou, - Yes.
在替谁偷工减料呢
Shitou, who are you helping to cheat?
师傅
But Master,
我练腿眼朝天
I was looking up.
没留神底下
I didn't notice what was on the floor.
废话
Bullshit.
- 取活去 - 噢
- Get my sword. - Okay.
快去
And hurry up!
现在来神了
Now it's coming
快点
Hurry up!
师傅
Master!
你起来
Get up!
怎么啦 你当是完啦
So that's it?
还有一说呐
Don't you have something to say?
是 在班结党者 罚
Yes. "Forming cliques is prohibited and will be punished."
我他妈小癞子 什么都不怕
I'm not fucking scared of anything.
打自有唱戏的行当起
From the time opera began,
每朝哪一代 它也没有咱们京戏 这么红过
it's never enjoyed such popularity as it does today!
你们算是赶上了
You're lucky to be part of it!
没错
For sure!
“此乃天亡我楚 非战之罪也”
Heaven's will, not a lack of soldierly skill, has doomed my kingdom.
小爷我今儿练的是 九转金浑火丹功
My little man, I've been practising the Taoist "kung fu of fire".
我到外...外...外边我 凉快 凉快去
It's cool outside, quite cool.
我成...火人了
But I've become a man of fire.
离...离我远点
Get away from me.
“力拔山兮 气盖世”
I am so strong I can uproot the mountains, My courage is renowned
“时不利兮 力拔山兮”
I've fallen on bad times, I can uproot the mountains.
“气盖世”
My courage is renowned
“时不利兮”
I've fallen on bad times,
“骓不逝”
yet even my horse won't run away to save itself
传于我辈门人 诸生须当敬听
These are our rules, we must learn them well.
自古人生于世 需有一技之能
From ancient times, man has needed a skill.
我辈既务斯业 便当专心用功
Having chosen this one, devote ourselves we will.
以后名扬四海 根据即在年轻
In youthful striving lies the foundations for future fame.
一边练去
Now go off and practise!
你的“夜奔”
Let's hear "Fleeing by Night".
“回首望天朝 急走忙逃”
I look back at the Celestial Court, and hurry onwards in flight...
“顾…顾不得…”
Heedless of... heedless of...
顾不得什么
Heed less of what?
“顾不得…”
Heedless of...
- “顾不得忠和孝” - 唉哟 “忠和孝”
- Heedless of loyalty and filial piety! - loyalty and filial piety!
“想俺项羽乎 力拔山兮气盖世”
I am so strong I can uproot the mountains, My courage is renowned
“时不利兮”
I've fallen on bad times,
“骓不逝”
yet even my horse won't run away to save itself
“骓不逝兮 可奈何”
If it won't run away, what can I do?
“虞姬虞姬 奈若何”
And my beloved concubine, what shall I do about her?
成 一字不差
Excellent, not a word out of place.
伸手
Give me your hand.
打你 是让你记着 下回还得这么背
This is so you'll remember to do as well next time.
“小尼姑 年方二八”
At sixteen l am a nun,
“正青春 被师傅削去了头发”
my hair shorn at youth's prime
下文呢
Go on.
“我本是男儿郎”
I am by nature a boy...
嗯
What?
“我…”
I...
“我本是…男儿郎”
I am by nature a boy...
你本是女娇娥
You are by nature a girl!
我需要你错…你错
Can't you see you're wrong!
啊 我打你个小癞子
I'll punish you, Laizi!
打
Punish you!
你还错 你要干嘛
You still can't get it right, can you?
你怎么唱的
How did you sing it?
小癞子再也不敢了
Don't hit me! I won't do it again!
再打
Again hit!
你的“思凡”
Sing "Dreaming of the World Outside the Nunnery".
“本是…我本是…我本是…我本是…”
I am... I am by nature...
你本是什么呀 啊
Spit it out!
“我本是 男儿郎”
I am by nature a boy...
尼姑是男的 还是女的
Is a nun male or female?
是…男儿郎
A boy.
您倒是真入了化境了
You really are in character.
连雌雄都不分了 啊
You can't even tell male from female.
“我…”
I...
“我本是…”
I am...
“男儿郎”
...by nature a boy
师傅说的戏 你全忘了
You've forgotten everything the master has taught you!
下次再忘
Do it again,
就往死里打你
and I'll beat you to within an inch of your life.
让你错 我让你错
Wrong! Wrong!
让你错 让你...
Wrong...
小子 长点记性
You'd better remember this.
磨剪子来
Bring your knives for sharpening!
镪菜刀
Sharpen your knives!
师哥
Bro.
赶明儿 我要是给打死了
If by chance I'm beaten to death tomorrow,
枕席底下 有三大子儿
I want you to have the three copper coins...
就给你了
...hidden under my mattress.
留神
Careful!
别进水
Don't let it touch the water.
手毁了 就唱不了戏了
If you ruin your hand, forget acting.
豆子
Douzi,
过两天 就要给祖师爷上香了
Douzi, in a few days, you'll be initiated into the troupe.
你就想你自己是个女的
You can think of yourself as a girl,
可别再背错了
just don't stuff up the lyrics again.
癞子
Laizi,
吃过豌豆黄吗
Laizi, have you ever eaten sweet pea cakes?
豌豆黄 豌豆黄算个屁呀
What's the big deal about sweet pea cakes?
吃过驴打滚吗
Have you ever had "Thrashing Donkey" millet rolls?
盆儿糕呢
"Basin cakes"?
都是他妈狗屁 不好吃
They're about as fucking special as dog farts.
那你说什么好吃啊
So what do you like?
天下最好吃的 冰糖葫芦数第一
There's nothing yummier than a stick of candied crab-apples.
我要是成了角儿
If I make it big,
天天得拿冰糖葫芦当饭吃
I'll eat candied crab-apples every day for dinner.
“冰糖葫芦 冰糖葫芦”
Candied crab-apples for sale!
甭这么瞧着朕
Don't look at us like that,
朕又不是冰糖葫芦
we're not a stick of candied crab-apples!
癞子 哈喇子都流出来了
Laizi, you're drooling!
你嘛呢你
What the hell are you doing?
- 回来 - 这么大个儿的风筝 一堆呢
- Get back here. - Wow, such big kites, and so many of them!
快回去 回去
Come back!
小豆子
Douzi!
快跑
Run for it!
跑了一个
Run a man.
站住
Hold it right there!
小豆子
Douzi!
师哥
Bro.
枕席底下 那三大子儿
Don't forget the copper cash...
你别忘了
...under my mattress.
反正你废了
You're worthless.
滚吧
Get out of my sight!
诶 哪儿来的
Hey, where'd you get that?
你那三大子儿买的啊
I bought it with your three copper coins.
小石头甭想花了 让朕受用了吧
Stuff Shitou, I'm spending your money now.
诶 一串十个 我给你俩怎么样
Ten apples on each stick. I'll give you two. How about it?
你怎么了 你啊
What's with you?
我憋了泡尿
I have to pee real bad.
诶 大街上可不许撒尿
You can't do it in the middle of the street.
靠边点 靠边点诶
Come on!
哎哟 王老板
It's Manager Wang!
角儿来了 角儿来了
The stars have arrived!
这儿有近道 走近道
Here, come this way.
哎哟 我的角儿诶 您这可是星宿下凡啦
Oh, my dear sir, this is indeed like a visitation from heaven!
您今儿就一声喷嚏 也得是满堂彩儿
All you need do is sneeze and you get a standing ovation.
您受累了
We've put you to so much trouble.
今天不挤出几条人命 就上上大吉了
It'll be pure luck if no one is trampled to death in there!
诶 你先驮着我 待会儿我驮着你呀
I'll sit on your shoulders for a while, then you sit on mine.
霸王 霸王诶
It's the king!
他们怎么成的角儿啊
What does it take to become a star?
得挨多少打啊
How many beatings?
我什么时候才能成角儿啊
When will we ever enjoy such fame?
- 诶 不 - 怎么意思诶
- No. - What's this?
你怎么尿我一脸呀你
You're pissing all over my face!
干嘛呀 你
What the hell are you doing?
我就知道 你要回来
I knew you'd want to go back.
离了小石头 你就活不了啦
You couldn't live without Shitou!
回去 你又得挨刀胚子
You're going to get a taste of the sword.
我可是不怕
Personally, I'm not afraid.
早就打皮实了
I've been beaten so much I'm tough as nails,
师傅打我 就跟挠痒痒似的
it's like having an itch scratched.
吃了糖葫芦
I've eaten my candied crab-apples.
我就是他妈角儿了
I'm a fucking star already!
我能怕谁啊
Who the hell do I have to be afraid of?
好小子 你们还回来呀 哪里跑
You little scamps, you've come back after all.
打得好 打得好
Good! I deserve it!
反了你了 叫你开门放人…
Why the hell did you let them go?
我打死你啊
I've had it with you!
背班逃跑者 罚
Skipping class and running away must be punished!
师傅 别打了 师傅 诶 师傅
Master, I'll never do it again.
下次再也不饶了我
Master, I'll never do it again. Please let me go!
你竟然跑
How dare you run
不要打豆子
Don't hit Douzi.
我叫你开门放人 你就放人 我打死你
Who told you to let them go? I'll kill you!
抓住他 抓住他
Catch him! Catch him!
师傅 你饶了我 下次再也不敢了
Master, I'll never do it again. Please let me go!
饶了我吧 师傅
Master, Please let me go!
师傅
Master,
是我自个儿跑的
Master, it was me who ran away.
不关师哥的事
He didn't have anything to do with it.
您打我
Beat me instead!
我叫你跑
I told you to run.
你有...
You..
我打死你
I'll kill you.
打死你呀
Kill you ah!
你以为我不敢打你呀
Did you think you wouldn't get yours?
你当我不打你
我打死你
I'll kill you.
豆子 说呀 说呀 开口呀
Douzi, speak! Say something!
讨个饶呀 说打得好呀 说呀
Beg for mercy! Say he's beaten you well and truly!
我打死你 你跑 你跑
I'll kill you! Run away, will you?
开口 说呀
Speak!
打死你
I'll beat you to death if I must.
打死你 咱们散伙儿
I'll beat you to death if I must. Let's just disband the troupe...
打
Beat!
打死你
I'll beat you to death if I must.
你把小豆子打死了
You're killing Douzi!
我跟你拼了
I won't let you do this!
关爷 关爷 可了不得了
Master Guan! Something terrible has happened!
这个 他…死了
Laizi, he...died.
“霸王别姬”
"Farewell My Concubine"
讲的是楚汉相争的故事
tells the story of the struggle between the Chu and Han kings.
楚霸王 何许人也
What sort of man was the King Of Chu?
那是天下无敌的盖世英雄
A peerless and invincible hero,
横扫千军的勇将猛帅
a bold and resourceful general capable of defeating vast armies.
可老天却偏偏不成全他
But fate wasn't on his side.
在垓下 中了汉军的十面埋伏
At Gaixia he fell into an ambush set by the Han king,
让刘邦给困死了
Liu Bang.
那天晚上 刮着大风
A great wind blew up on that night.
刘邦的兵 唱了一宿的楚歌
Liu Bang's troops sang the songs of the kingdom of Chu all night long.
楚国的人马 以为刘邦得了楚地
The Chu warriors assumed Liu Bang already occupied their homeland.
全都慌了神了 跑光了
In a great panic, they fled.
听得霸王 也掉下泪来
Even the king was weeping.
人纵有万般能耐
No matter how resourceful you are,
可终也敌不过天命
you can't fight fate.
那霸王风云一世
The king had once been all-powerful,
临到头
but in the end,
就剩下了 一匹马和一个女人 还跟着他
all he had left was one woman and one horse.
霸王让乌骓马逃命 乌骓马不去
He tried to get his steed to run away, but it wouldn't go.
让虞姬走人 虞姬不肯
He wanted his concubine to flee, but she stayed too.
那虞姬 最后一次为霸王斟酒
For the very last time, Concubine Yu poured wine for her king
最后一回 为霸王舞剑
and danced for him with a sword,
尔后 拔剑自刎 从一而终啊
then cut her throat with it, faithful to the king unto death.
讲这出戏
There's a lesson...
是这里边 有个唱戏和做人的道理
...in this story for all of us
人 得自个儿成全自个儿
that each person is responsible for his or her own fate.
“力拔山兮”
I am so strong I can uproot the mountains,
“气盖世”
My courage is renowned.
“时不利兮”
I've fallen on bad times,
“骓不逝”
Yet even my horse won't run away to save itself
张宅上 把订戏的差 委了您…
Old Man Zhang has commissioned you to hire an opera troupe.
那您就是 我们喜福成的衣食父母
You're like a fairy godmother to us.
啊 您抬举抬举呢
With your patronage,
孩子们年下 就穿上新衣裳了
the children will have new clothes to wear in the New Year.
衣裳的事 好穿
New clothes are not a problem.
戏活难做
The opera, however, is no simple matter.
诶 对啊
Yes.
张公公 那是当年
When he was a palace eunuch, Old Man Zhang...
陪太后老佛爷 听过戏的主儿
...attended operas with the Empress Dowager herself.
那是 那是
That's it.
糊弄得了吗
So you can't put anything over on him.
敢吗
Not that anyone would try!
玩艺儿要是不灵 新衣裳…
You realise that if this little number doesn't make the grade,
砸了我的脸面 没什么
I could lose a lot of face, but that's nothing.
- 像您这样的 - 啊
- He could... - Me?
能把您给囚起来
He could have you locked up!
- 这孩子 有点意思啊 - 啊
- This kid's got something. - What?
学几年戏啦 啊
How many years has he been in training?
小豆子 快 快 过来 过来
Douzi, come here...
来给经...经理请安啦
...and pay your respects.
嗯
Oh,
身段 也还不错
He's got a nice little figure, too.
有点昆腔儿的底儿没有啊
Can you sing any old-style operas?
诶... 学了两出
Yes, two.
男怕“夜奔” 女怕“思凡”
"Dreaming of the World Outside the Nunnery" is the hardest female role.
就来段“思凡”吧
Let's hear a bit of it.
“小尼姑 年方二八”
At sixteen I am a nun
“正青春 被师傅削去了头发”
my hair shorn at youth's prime
“我本是男儿郎 又不是女娇娥”
Yet I am by nature a boy, not a girl
“为何…”
Why...
诶 那爷 嗯 那爷
Mr Na,
实在是对不住您哪
I am truly sorry! He's usually very good.
实在是对不住
I am truly sorry!
- 回头见 改日再见 - 这孩子平常不是这样的
- This kid doesn't usually do that. - Master Guan, I'll see you some other time.
谁叫你回来啦 我叫你错…
Who told you to come back here? You screwed up bad!
张嘴 张嘴 张嘴
Open your mouth. Open it!
错 错呀你
You've stuffed it up!
叫你错
叫你错 我叫你错 我叫你错 错呀你 错…
You've stuffed it up! Stuffed it up!
拿来
Come here!
“我本是…”
I am...
“我本是女娇娥 又不是…”
I am by nature a girl, not a boy...
“小尼姑年方二八”
At sixteen l am a nun
“正青春 被师傅削去了头发”
My hair shorn at youth's prime
“我本是女娇娥 又不是男儿郎”
Yet I am by nature a girl, not a boy
“为何腰系黄绦 身穿直掇”
Why must I wear these sexless robes?
“见人家夫妻们洒落”
I see the joyful couples pass
“一对对着锦穿罗 不由人心急似火”
In their splendid brocades. Despite myself, desire burns in my heart.
“奴把袈裟扯破”
And I rend my Buddhist gown!
“自从我...”
For year upon year,
“随大王…”
all over the land, I've followed my king...
“东征西战…”
...on his military campaigns
“受风霜与劳碌 年复年年…”
Enduring the wind, And frost and hard toil
“恨只恨无道秦”
I hate only the lawless tyrant,
“把生灵涂炭”
Who has plunged our people into an abyss of misery!
哎嗨 哎…
This little boy...
诶 关爷 关爷
Master Guan...
张公公 您寿比南山
Mr Zhang, may you live as long as South Mountain.
“只害得众百姓痛苦颠连”
The people have suffered, Untold hardship and pain
“大王回营呀”
The King has returned to the camp!
“大王”
Your Highness!
“此一番 连累你 多受惊慌”
I've caused you so much grief
这是老公公
This is...
特特地赏给 两位小角儿的啊 谢赏去吧
...a token of the old man's appreciation for the two young actors.
喳
Yes, sir!
霸王要是有这把剑
If the king had had this sword,
早就把刘邦给宰了
he'd have wiped out Liu Bang ages ago!
当上了皇上
If I were emperor,
嘿 那你就是正宫娘娘了
If I were emperor, then you'd be queen of the palace.
师哥 我准送你这把剑
I want you to have a sword like this.
诶 哎哟 当心呢
Careful,
当心咯 我的小爷儿 当真
Careful, my little man!
这可是把真家伙
That's a real blade!
慢着
Don't run...
来了 来了 来了
Here we are.
怎么啦
What's wrong?
眉毛这儿 汗一蛰 生疼
It stings when the sweat gets into a scratch over my eye.
俩孩子 一块儿去吧
Aren't the two kids going in together?
老规矩了
No.
- 多少年的老规矩了 - 诶
- It's an old rule around here. - Right.
关师傅
Master Guan,
这您不明白 就说不过去了
Master Guan, if you don't understand, there's nothing I can say.
您说这虞姬她怎么演的
The concubine...
可她也得有一死不是
The concubine has to die one way or the other.
您说呢
Isn't it so?
师傅…
Master?
小豆子
Douzi!
小豆子啊
今年是什么年
What year is this?
是...
It's...
民国 二十一年
...the 21st year of the Republic, 1932.
不对
Wrong.
是大清宣统 二十四年
It's the 24th year of Emperor Xuantong's rein.
你 过来
Come over here.
我…我
I...
我找我师哥
I want Shitou.
我...我想撒尿
I have to pee!
就往这里头撒
Do it in this. Aim in here.
你这样的往里头撒 不算糟塌东西
You won't harm anything.
来
Come over.
诶...来呀
Come to me!
豆子
Douzi!
关老板
Master Guan.
- 张公公 让我谢谢您 - 你怎么了 说话呀
- Mr. Zhang asked me to thank you. - What's happened to you? Say something!
哑巴啦
Have you gone dumb?
说话呀
Speak to me!
小豆子
Douzi,
一个人 有一个人的命
fate has determined each of our lots.
你还是把他 放回去吧
Leave him to his destiny.
好了…好勒...
All right,
瞧这儿…
look at the camera!
二位老板 少年裘马
You two young gentlemen have done grandly for yourselves.
甭管穿什么衣裳 什么款式
You look so dignified, absolutely striking,
只要一上身 保管你都体面 都标致
in any style of clothing.
好
That's it!
“反对日本增兵华北”
Oppose Japan's invasion of North China!
糟了糟了 又是那些学生
Damn! It's those students again.
“保卫华北 打倒日本帝国主义”
Down with Japanese imperialism! Death is preferable to enslavement!
喂 这不是照片上那俩戏子吗
Aren't those the two actors in the photograph?
眼瞅就要当亡国奴了 你知道吗
Don't you know you're playing into the hands of the Japanese?
妖里妖气的 你唱什么戏
Yeah, how can you tart yourself up and sing opera at a time like this?
没家没国的 你们有没有中国人的良心
Don't you have the least bit of feeling for your country?
都看清楚啦 啊
Take a good look.
这是正经八百的中国人
We're Chinese too. Chinese to the core!
你们他妈都给我 看清楚了
Look at us, goddamn it!
没错 没错 正经八百中国人
That's right, that's right, we're all Chinese here!
中国人不打中国人
Chinese mustn't fight among themselves!
都是一个老祖宗
We're all descended from the same ancestors!
老祖宗错得了吗 错不了 错不了
And don't you forget it!
一个个都他妈忠臣良将的模样
Every goddamn one of them thinks he's a super-patriot.
这日本兵就在城外头 打去呀
The Japanese soldiers aren't far away, they should go fight them.
敢情欺负的还是中国人呀
Instead, they pick on fellow Chinese!
瞎哄呗 学生们不都没娶过媳妇吗
They're just looking for trouble. None of them have married yet,
火气壮 又没钱找姑娘
and they've got no money to get any girls,
总得找个地界 撒撒火气是不是 你说
so they've got to let off steam somehow.
领着喊的那个 唱武生倒不错
Their leader would make a good player of military roles!
诶
Hey,
咱们第一出"别姬" 在哪儿唱的来着
Where was it that we first performed "Farewell"?
这驴年马月的事 全让你记住了
You usually remember every silly little detail.
诶诶...段老板 您这不能忘啰
Oh, Mr Duan, I remember.
那不张公公府上堂会吗
It was at the home of Old Man Zhang.
我保的二位小爷嘛
My good men,
- 二位的发祥宝地 是不  - 那是
- it was from there that your careers took off! - Yes.
蝶衣
Dieyi,
那儿现成了棺材铺了
Zhang's home is now a coffin shop!
我昨儿刚去的
I went there just yesterday.
又去找那把剑去了 是不
You were looking for that sword, weren't you?
早不知卖哪儿去了
It was probably sold off years ago.
程蝶衣…程蝶衣…
Cheng Dieyi! Cheng Dieyi!
冰糖葫芦
Candied crab-apples for sale!
座是汪洋汪海…
There's a sea of awestruck people in there
一个个都伸着脖子
craning their necks to catch...
等着赡仰 您二位风采呢
...a glimpse of their idols.
袁四爷
Master Yuan...
专门捧您的场子
...has come specially to see you perform tonight.
您这面子 天大的去了
It's a great honour for us.
马后 马后…没扮上呢
There'll be a slight delay!
段老板
Mr Duan...
急急风催半天了
The orchestra's been warming up for ages.
您再紧把手
Please hurry!
知道了 知道了
I know. I know.
我先亮一嗓子
Let me first practise a few scales.
让他们知道 票没白买 不就得了
That way they'll know they'll be getting their money's worth.
四爷
Master Yuan!
“自从我”
Year after year, all over the land,
“随大王东征西战”
I've followed my king on his military campaigns
“受风霜与劳碌年复年年”
Enduring the wind, And frost and hard toil
四爷 您说到没到
You judge...
那人戏不分 雌雄同在的境界
has he not blurred the distinction between theatre and life...
您给断断
male and female?
“恨...恨...”
I hate...
“大王”
Your Highness!
“此一番连累你”
I've caused you...
“多受惊慌”
...so much grief
诶 袁四爷今儿个 来捧场了
So, Master Yuan has come to see us tonight.
没听见我盖着哨呐唱吗
Didn't you hear me sing so loudly I drowned out the horns?
把血都挣出来了
My face went red.
我就让他听明白了
But I wanted him to know that without his patronage,
没他四爷的捧场
we'd still be the talk...
咱在北平 也照唱照红
...of the town here in Peiping.
那你也悠着点
You shouldn't exert yourself like that.
没事儿
Don't worry.
到了裉节上
At key moments,
我两手轮着撑在腰里
I squeezed my waist with my hands
帮着提气
so I wouldn't get out of breath.
这儿
Here?
不对
No.
这儿
Here?
嗯
Yes.
- 这儿 - 唉哟 我不行 你别闹
- Here! - Stop it!
哟 四爷
Master Yuan!
久仰久仰
It's an honour.
二位果然是不负盛名
Your reputation turns out to be well-deserved.
四爷
Master Yuan!
您捧场
You're very kind.
唐突了点
Please accept a small,
算是见面礼
rather slapdash token of my esteem.
哎哟喂
Oh, hello
都说当年太后老佛爷
I don't believe the Empress Dowager herself ever
诶 她老人家赏戏 有这样的手面吗
bestowed such a gift upon her favourite actors.
有吗
If so,
没有吧
I'd never heard of it!
四爷
Master Yuan,
您这让我们蝶衣 怎么当得起啊
how can our Dieyi be worthy of your favour?
“霸王别姬”这一折
"Farewell My Concubine"...
渊源已久
...has a long history.
本是从昆剧老本
It evolved from...
“千金记”里脱胎出来的
...the old-style opera "The Gold Strategy".
好多名家 都在这出上唱栽过
Many famous actors have fallen down in this role.
独你程老板的虞姬
Your evocation of the Concubine Yu...
快入纯青之境
...lifts it into a higher realm.
有点意思
Impressive.
有那么一二刻
For a moment or two,
袁某也恍惚起来
this Yuan fellow was so entranced
疑为虞姬 转世再现啦
he believed Concubine Yu had actually come back to life!
段老板…
Mr Duan...
霸王回营亮相
when the king returns to camp...
到和虞姬相见
...and meets Concubine Yu,
按老规矩…
custom has it...
是 四爷
Yes, Master Yuan.
按老规矩是定然七步 你只走了五步
Custom has it he takes seven steps. Yet you take but five.
楚霸王 气度尊贵
If the King of Chu fails to bear himself with majestic dignity,
要是威而不重
he's little better than...
不成了江湖上的黄天霸了
...a gangster putting on airs!
四爷
Master Yuan,
您梨园大拿呀
you are a master of the theatre arts.
文武昆乱不挡 六场通透
You are expert in all the varieties and facets of opera.
您能有错吗
Could we doubt your word?
- 哦 - 您要是都出了错
- Yes. - Indeed,
那我们兄弟 这点玩艺儿…
we are presumptuous to parade our meagre talents...
还敢在北平的戏园子里露吗
in the theatres of Peiping.
四爷 您得栽培我们
Please give us the benefit of your advice and criticism.
如不嫌弃
If it's not beneath you,
请二位到舍下 小酌几杯 然后细谈
I'd like to invite you to my humble home for some wine.
实话说
There is...
这出戏的学问 还真是不浅
There is so much still to be said about this opera.
哟 四爷
Master Yuan,
对您不住
I'm terribly sorry.
赶巧了
Sorry!
我得…
I've another...
喝一壶花酒去
...drinking engagement with a courtesan.
另有雅趣
You have other refined entertainments planned!
好
Excellent!
程老板呢
And Mr Cheng?
我...
Me...
那么日后踏雪访梅
Then we shall exchange poetic thoughts...
再谈不迟
...some other day.
失陪了
I'll take my leave.
四爷 您慢走
Take care, Master Yuan.
- 蝶衣 - 诶
- Dieyi, - What?
我也走了
Dieyi, I'm off as well.
彩凤 金燕 丽君 淑瑷 秋香
Caifeng, Jinyan, Lijun, Shuyuan, Qiuxiang...
接客了
come entertain our guest.
哟 段老板 您来啦
Mr Duan, this way please.
段老板
Mr Duan,
段老板 您有些日子没来了 太久了...
We haven't seen you for a while, Mr Duan.
这心里还怪惦记的
We've missed you.
会会菊仙姑娘
I'd like to see Miss Juxian.
哟 这话怎么说的呢
Ah, how shall I put it?
您倒早…
You should...
您倒早言语呀
You should have said something earlier.
菊仙姑娘 这阵子不在
She's not here at the moment.
她出条子 应饭局子去了
She was asked out to dinner.
这可怎么好啊 要不这么着吧
What to do? How about this...
姐给你找个好的 啊
We'll find you a good substitute.
彩凤
Caifeng,
- 诶 - 你来陪陪段老板
- What? - come keep Mr Duan company!
小楼 我就不陪你了
I'll take my leave.
给哥哥透个实情
Tell me the truth.
菊仙姑娘 在哪间屋啊
Where is Juxian really?
是在底下呀 还是在上头
Upstairs or... down?
凤凰当然栖高枝啦
The phoenix roosts on the highest branches of course!
可人家是头牌
But she's pretty high class.
你够得着吗
You reckon she'll go for you?
让你说着了
You said it!
哥哥我就是 专傍头牌的
I specialise in high class.
哎呀 菊仙姑娘…
Oh, Miss Juxian...
你王八蛋
Bastards!
王八蛋就王八蛋
OK, we're bastards!
去呀
Go for it then.
- 你不是要傍头牌吗 - 嗯
- What are you waiting for? - Yes.
看这几位爷 不把你剁了当菜吃
Let's see if those guys don't just make mincemeat of you!
我告诉你 我真急了
I'm really angry now!
咹 这...急...急了 好呀
We like it when you're angry!
再闹
Cut it out...
再闹我跳了
or I'll jump!
跳呀 你跳呀
Jump!
你前脚跳 我后脚跳
I'll follow on your heels.
宁在花下死 做鬼也风流
Such a death would be ecstasy. I'd be a merry ghost.
我们就跟你死
If you die, we'll all die,
做你棺材板
and be the planks in your coffin.
小楼
Xiaolou!
这帮小子坏透了
These guys are revolting!
他们逼着我 嘴对嘴地喂他们酒喝
They were forcing me to drink wine from their mouths.
怎么着 王八蛋 你们跳呀
Come on, assholes. Jump!
姑奶奶跳了 怎么着
This lady's done it. Now's your turn!
王八蛋
Bastards!
都是她妈丫头养的
Pack of fucking sissies!
下去就他妈下去 下去 走
All right, if we have to go down, let's go!
是段老板呐
Oh, it's Mr Duan!
段老板
Listen,
咱们到这儿来 可都是来找乐子的
we're all here to have a good time,
扔出去的 可都是白花花响当当的大洋啊
and we're all spending good money.
今儿个
So...
谁跟谁 都别找不痛快
...let's not pick fights with each other.
别找不痛快
Don't look for trouble.
走吧 走吧
Get out of here.
松手
Let go.
- 喂 别介呀… - 别介
- Don't get upset. - - Don't get upset?
怂啦
Scared?
菊仙
Juxian,
这可就是你的不周到了
this is all really your fault.
你怎么没告诉各位爷 今儿是什么日子
Didn't you tell these gentlemen today's a special day?
今儿个 不是咱俩定亲的喜日子吗
That we decided to announce our engagement today?
对
That's right!
今儿个 是姑奶奶定亲的喜日子
Today is this lady's happy day.
怎么着
So?
给姑奶奶贺喜吧
Aren't you going to offer your congratulations?
给姑奶奶敬酒吧
Drink a toast to me!
爷们儿 哄他妈谁呢
Who the fuck are they kidding?
- 哟 各位爷 - 你笨
- Gentlemen, - You're stupid.
今儿是我大喜的日子
on this, my happiest day...
滚开
Get ou!
我得敬敬各位爷
allow me to drink to all of you!
给各位爷 醒醒酒
And now something to sober you up.
给我叫一好
Wish us well!
诶 小楼
Xiaolou,
听说 您在八大胡同打出名来了
I heard you got into a fight at the House of Blossoms.
唵 啊
What?
这武二郎 碰上西门庆了
You know the old story about Pan Jinlian's husband
不打
meeting the man who screwed her?
不打 能成吗
Did he have any choice but to fight?
这么说 有个潘金莲啦
Does this mean there's a Pan Jinlian in your life?
这是什么话
What are you saying?
你想听什么话
What do you want to hear?
嗨
Hi.
不过是救人解难 玩玩呗
I was just fooling around. "Damsel in distress"...
又不当真
and all that - no big deal.
蝶衣
Dieyi,
什么时候 一块儿去逛逛
Come there with me sometime.
就知道了
You'll see what it's like.
嘿呦
Hey, yo.
兄弟
Bro.
哟
Hey.
对不住 兄弟
I'm sorry. I really am!
师哥今儿 神不在家
I just wasn't thinking.
自己是...是
I really...
说走嘴了
...put my foot in it this time.
师哥该死
I'm a damn fool.
你忘了
Have you forgotten...
咱们是怎么唱红的
...the secret of our success?
还不就凭了师傅一句话
Don't you remember our teacher's words?
什么话呀
Which words were they?
从一而终
Stick together till the day you die.
师哥
Bro.
我要让你跟我...
I want you to be with me...
不对...
I mean...
就让我跟你 好好唱一辈子戏
I want to be with you the rest of my life.
不行吗
Can't we?
这不…
We've...
这不 小半辈子都唱过来了吗
We've come this far together, haven't we?
不行
It's not enough.
说的是一辈子
I'm talking about a lifetime.
差一年 一个月 一天 一个时辰
One year, one month, one day, even one second less
都不算一辈子
makes it less than a lifetime!
蝶衣
Dieyi,
你可真是 不疯魔 不成活呀
Dieyi, you really are obsessed.
唱戏得疯魔 不假
You're obsessed on stage...
可要是活着 也疯魔
and it carries over into your life.
在这人世上 在这凡人堆里
But how are we going to get through the days and make it
咱们可怎么活哟
in the real world, among ordinary people?
来 给师哥勾个脸
Give me a hand with my makeup, will you?
“妃子”
Oh my concubine!
“四面俱是楚国歌声”
The songs of Chu can be heard on all sides!
“定是刘邦得了楚地 孤大势去矣”
Liu Bang has surely taken my kingdom! I'm finished!
“啊 大王”
My king!
“依孤看来”
I fear...
“今日是你我分别之日了”
...that today is the day we must part
真他妈想当太太奶奶啦 你
So you want to become a fucking hoity-toity rich man's wife!
做你娘的玻璃梦 去吧
Go live out this goddamn fantasy then.
你当出了这门儿 把脸一抹洒
But you're kidding yourself if you think that when you walk out this door,
你还真成了良人啦
you'll become a lady of virtue!
你当这世上的狼啊虎啊
You think the wolves and tigers...
就都不认得你啦
...won't recognise your scent anymore?
哟
Hey,
可吓死我啦
How you frighten me!
我告诉你
Let me tell you something.
那窑姐儿 永远是窑姐儿
Once a whore, always a whore.
你记住我这话
Just remember that.
这就是你的命
This is your fate!
成
Fine.
回见了您呐
See you around.
袁四爷送条幅
Master Yuan has presented you with a pennant.
“风华绝代”
It reads, "The beauty of the age".
程蝶衣 程老板
Dieyi Cheng, Mr Cheng!
咦哟
Eh, yo.
你怎么上这儿来了
What are you doing here?
又怎么了 菊仙
What is it, Juxian?
来 来 来 进来
Come on in!
进来说
你出来
No, you come out!
对诶 怎么光着脚啊 这么凉的天
What are you doing barefoot on such a cold day?
出了什么事啦
What's happened?
赶出来了
I was kicked out.
花满楼 不留许过婚的人
The House of Blossoms won't keep an engaged woman.
程老板 程老板
Mr Cheng,
来...来
Come.
来 过来 过来见见
Come. Let me introduce you.
这是 菊仙小姐
This is Miss Juxian.
这就是我的亲师弟
This is my stage brother.
你瞧见了 演虞姬的
You've seen him as Concubine Yu.
哟
Hey,
常听小楼念叨您
Xiaolou speaks of you so often,
听都听成熟人了
I feel like we're old friends.
噢 菊仙小姐 失陪了
Ah, Miss Juxian. I must be going.
小楼
Xiaolou,
那天在花满楼
that day at the House of Blossoms...
要不是 你在楼底下接着
If you hadn't caught me,
我早就入土了
I'd be six feet under by now.
那杯定亲酒 可是你先喝了一半
Remember, it was you who proposed to me.
菊仙命苦
I'm used to hardship.
你要是收留她
If you take me in...
有人当牛做马 侍侯你
I'll wait on you hand and foot.
你要是嫌弃她
If you tire of me,
大不了 她再跳回楼
I'll jump again and kill myself. No big deal, really.
这妞可够厉害的
What a dragon lady!
服 我服 啊
Incredible!
这他妈就是一本大戏呀
This is a major production.
什么时候 洞房花烛夜呀
When's the performance of "Candlelit Night in the Bridal Chamber"?
今儿晚上
Tonight.
好 好
Great!
还有哪
Hold on.
你呀 得当着戏班子 老少爷们的面儿
I want a formal betrothal ceremony...
先给我办定亲礼
...to which the entire company is invited.
我得堂堂正正地 进你段家的门
I want to enter your home as a proper bride.
嫌我偷工减料啊
You don't think I plan to cut corners, do you?
那成 今儿晚上就是定亲礼
The formal engagement ceremony will be tonight.
我请各位赏光
Gentlemen, we request the pleasure of your company.
菊仙小姐
Miss Juxian...
您挨哪儿 学的戏啊
where did you study opera?
哟
Oh.
我哪儿学过戏呀
Me, study opera? What makes you think I studied opera?
没学过呀 那就别洒狗血了
Just the way you're overplaying your part.
蝶衣
Dieyi,
叫声嫂子吧
she's like your sister-in-law now.
不叫不成了
Call her that.
还有今儿晚上 证婚人这活儿
Also, at the engagement party tonight...
你得给我接下来
I'd like you to be best man.
黄天霸和妓女的戏 不会演
I haven't learnt the opera "Gangster King and his Whore".
师傅没教过
Our teacher never taught us that one.
这...这是哪儿和哪儿呢
What are you on about?
师弟
Dieyi,
小楼在人前人后提起您来
Xiaolou has never said an ill word about you
说的 可都是厚道话儿
in public or private.
别走
Don't leave!
你上哪儿去
Where are you going?
我上哪儿去 你管得着吗
None of your business.
- 诶 小... - 师哥
- Hey, Xiao... - Xiaolou!
师哥 你别走
Please don't go!
袁四爷今儿晚上 请咱们过去
Master Yuan wants us to visit him tonight.
要栽培咱们
He wants to become our patron.
姓袁的 他管得着姓段的吗
Who does he think he is? No one tells me what to do.
我是假霸王 你是真虞姬
I'm just a fake king. You really are Concubine Yu.
让他栽培你一个人去吧
Let him patronise you if you like.
师哥
Xiaolou!
这对翎子 难得
A headdress of this quality is a rare thing.
是从活雉鸡的尾巴上 生生收取的
Only if plucked from the tail of a live pheasant
这才够柔软
are the feathers so soft,
够伶俐
lithe...
够漂亮
...and beautiful.
我恭候大驾啦
I respectfully await your good self!
尘世中
In this world,
男子阳污 女子阴秽
there is foulness in both men and women.
独观世音 集两者之精 于一身
Only the Bodhisattva embodies both male and female essences.
欢喜无量啊
Such ecstasy!
这把剑 有些来历
This sword has a history.
是大太监张某的旧物
It once belonged to the eunuch Zhang.
张家破败时
When Zhang went bankrupt,
是费了大周折 弄到手的
I went to great trouble to acquire it.
如此看来…
I can see from this
此物是你的旧相识了
you're old acquaintances.
果然世上的事
Amazing, one searches far and wide for something...
是踏破铁鞋无觅处啊
...only to stumble upon it by chance.
喜欢
Like it?
我…
I...
你我之间不言钱 那个字眼实在不雅
Let's not have any vulgar talk of money between us.
自古宝剑酬知已
A precious sword is the classic gift for one's most intimate friend.
程老板
Mr Cheng,
愿做我的红尘知己吗
Mr Cheng, will you be my most intimate friend?
“汉兵已略地”
The soldiers of Han have invaded
“四面楚歌声”
The songs of Chu can be heard on all sides
不
No.
“君王意气尽”
Since the good king has lost his fighting spirit
“贱妾何聊生”
Why should his humble concubine value her life?
别动
Don't!
这是真家伙
It's a real sword!
一笑万古春
A smile ushers in the spring...
一啼万古愁
A tear does darken all the world.
此境 非你莫属
How truly does this befit you...
此貌 非你莫有
Only you are possessed of such charm.
回来
Come back.
不要跑
Don't run!
哎哟 嘿嘿
Ah,
程老板 准知道你就得回来啊
Mr Cheng. I knew you'd come.
这上座都给您留着哪
We saved a seat at the head table for you.
小楼
Xiaolou!
好你个蝶衣
Well if it isn't Dieyi!
这面子 你总算给师哥了
So you've decided to give me some face at last.
要不然
Otherwise...
你认认
Have a look at this.
好剑
Great sword!
又不上台
But we're not on stage.
要剑干什么
What would I want with a sword?
啊
Why?
师弟呀
Dieyi,
今儿个 你可来晚了
you've come so late.
该罚你一杯
I ought to punish you by making you drink this.
对 得罚一杯
Yes, drink up!
多谢菊仙小姐
My gratitude, Miss Juxian.
- 啊 蝶衣 - 程老板…
- Dieyi. - Mr Cheng.
小楼
Xiaolou,
从今往后
from now on,
你唱你的 我唱我的
we'll go our own ways.
嘿 别呀 我的程老板 这可不能够
Mr Cheng, you can't do this!
这不是 让人笑话吗
Isn't this funny?
戏迷们 还不得要…
the fans won't...
了...了不得
This is terrible!
日本…日本进城 进城
Japanese troops have entered the city!
蝶衣 蝶衣呢
Dieyi... where's Dieyi?
“启娘娘 高力士敬酒”
I, Gao Lishi. respectfully bring you some wine
“高力士”
Gao Lishi,
“你敬的什么酒”
what is this wine you bring me?
“奴牌敬的乃是通宵酒”
The wine brought by my unworthy self is called all-night wine
“呀呀啐”
Oh dear!
“哪个与你们通宵”
And who will spend all night with you?
师弟说
Dieyi says...
这眉子 得勾得立着点 才有味
the eyebrows look best if they've got a strong line.
“人生在世如春梦”
Life's like a dream of spring
“您那且自开怀吧”
To your heart's content!
“且自开怀饮几盅”
I shall drink to my heart's content
一会儿...
wait a moment...
嗨
Yes.
段老板 你看这个
Look at this, Mr Duan...
太君 我给您系上
Taijun, I'll tie it for you.
诶
Hey,
这不成 你得让他给我脱下来
I won't stand for it! Tell him to take it off immediately.
小楼
Xiaolou!
停电了…
The power is out...
停得好啊
OK...
好
这才是你的戏衣
What's the fuss? It's only a costume.
他就要你姥姥身上的寿衣
If it was the shroud out of your grandma's coffin,
你得乖乖的给扒下来
you'd still have to give it to me.
听明白了吗 戏子
Get my meaning? Low-life actor!
不要怕 喔 还有什么
Don't be afraid. What else is there
跟日本人说 我马上就去
Tell the Japanese I'll be there right away.
诶 诶 诶
Hey,
慢着喔
Hold on a tick!
这哪儿是什么堂会呀
It's not some private party.
这就是讹您啦 去给他们唱一回去
It's a blackmail.
您说这不去吧 眼下能救小楼的
On the one hand, you're the only one...
除了您 没旁人了
...who can save Xiaolou.
您要是去吧
On the other,
万一您自个儿 再出点什么差池
if anything happened to you...
我这个戏园子 我去...
this theatre of mine, it would...
诶 得
All right,
好 去 去 啊 去
All right, go then.
诶 菊仙小姐 菊仙小姐 您干什么 小的...
Miss Juxian, what are you doing? I...
小姐 程老板不在家
Miss, Miss... Mr Cheng isn't at home!
蝶衣呢
Where's Dieyi? Dieyi?
蝶衣 你赶紧的呀
Hurry!
都说日本人
They say the Japanese...
会放狼狗 掏人心吃
...let their dogs eat the hearts right out of people's chests.
他又是那个脾气
And you know Xiaolou's temper.
你要去晚了 他可就没命啦
If you delay, he mightn't have a life to save!
师弟
Dieyi!
我师哥 可是在您的手上 让人逮走的
But you allowed them to take him away in the first place.
诶 你这是什么话嘛
What are you saying?
小楼打小 是怎么待你的
Xiaolou has looked after you since you were small.
您知道就好
Glad you're aware of that too.
那爷
Mr Na,
诶 嘿
Right.
请您先退一步
would you mind leaving the room for a moment?
诶 好
Okay!
我跟我师弟 有几句私房话要说
I have something to say to Dieyi in private.
都说菊仙姑娘聪明
Everyone says Miss Juxian is quite clever,
不然不能这时候来
and her timing in this case certainly proves it.
都是为了小楼 啊
We're all trying to help Xiaolou.
有话好商量 诶
Talk it over.
干脆明说了吧
How about a clear answer,
您倒是去 还是不去
are you going or not?
说话呀 你
Say something!
我明白你的心思
I know what's on your mind.
要不这么着吧
I have a proposal.
你只要囫囵个地 把小楼给弄出来
If you can get Xiaolou out of there in one piece,
我哪来哪去 回我的花满楼
I'll go back to the House of Blossoms.
躲你们俩远远的
I'll keep away from both of you then.
成了吧
How's that?
要说在花满楼
At the House of Blossoms,
还真是个不操闲心的地方
you don't have to worry about much.
日子过得轻省多了
Life is a lot simpler there.
这可是您自个儿说的
Just remember, you said it, not me.
一言为定
I give my word.
“姹紫嫣红开遍”
The flowers have blossomed, Their season's past
“似这般 都付于断井颓垣”
All has fallen, into ruin and decay
“良辰美景奈何天”
The sun shines brightly, over the beautiful scene
“便赏心乐事谁家院”
But is there anyone left, to enjoy it?
- 小楼呢 - 哎呀 小楼
- Where is Xiaolou? - Xiaolou!
师哥
My brother!
- 师哥 - 小楼
- Bro. - Xiaolou!
师哥
My brother!
小楼 你没事吧
Xiaolou, are you all right?
你给日本人唱了
Did you sing for the Japanese?
有个叫青木的
There's one called Aoki.
他是懂戏的
He's quite a fan of Peking Opera
小楼 你
Xiaolou!
举枪
Raise a gun!
发射
Fire!
我好了
All right.
来吧
Come here!
我再喝一杯
Let me have another drink.
对不起 我…我替你喝
I... I'll drink for you.
嗯 来
Come on!
这就是“霸王别姬”
I think this opera "Farewell My Concubine"
依我之见
has turned...
你们这戏 演到这份儿上
...into...
竟成了姬别霸王
..."Farewell My King".
没霸王什么看头
The king doesn't really get a look in.
喝了它
Drink this...
您定能纤音入云
and your voice will pierce the heavens,
柔情胜水
yet be tender and fluid as water.
别动
Don't move!
好
Right.
不唱戏了
Forget the opera.
往后啊
Let's just...
我太太平平地跟你过日子
live a quiet life.
再生个大胖小子
We'll have a fat little baby boy.
我一下得俩
And I'll have everything I want.
够了
That's enough.
不唱戏了
No more opera.
哎 走 走…
Let's go.
赶紧走 弄一个破虫子
Hurry up! Take those wretched insects!
大哥 我走了 再见啊
See you, pal.
行了 行了…
All right, all right!
嘿
Hey,
拿出来
Hand it over!
谁要你这破蛐蛐
I'm not talking about your stupid crickets.
你借他的钱呢
Where's the money he lent you?
我这是...
I...
你别看他今儿个高兴 想讹他
Don't think you can take advantage of him when he's in a good mood.
把钱拿出来 赶紧的
Give me the money and get lost.
玩蛐蛐 大爷乐意
I'm the one who wanted them.
赶紧走吧
Piss off!
站起来 都是七尺高的老爷们儿
A man's no longer a man if he gives up a proper job
放正经营生 不做
to waste all his time...
在一个小虫子身上找饭摺
...on these stupid insects.
德行
Disgusting!
正经营生
A proper job?
我姓段的就会唱戏
All I can do is sing
啊 戏你不让我唱了
and you won't stand for that.
我不玩蛐蛐 我干嘛去啊
What am I supposed to do?
我抬棺材 掏大粪去
Find work as a pallbearer? A night soil carrier?
我...
I...
我放...
I throw...
得 这下您乐了吧
Would that make you happy?
瞧你
Look at you!
真生气啦
You're really angry?
拿着
Take this back.
你还没完啦
Not through yet?
得
Right.
算我话说重了 成了吧
So I overstated things a bit. OK?
哎 你要是不这么着啊
If you're not careful,
他们就像那狗尿苔似的 长咱们家了
these people will be all over us like fungus.
诶
Hey,
科班那个 关老爷子说 让你去哪
Oh, your old teacher wants you to go see him.
不去 没脸见师傅
I'm not going. I'm too ashamed of myself.
“看那剑”
Look at that sword!
老爷子 他们都到了
Sir, they're here!
谁呀
Who?
蝶衣 小楼
Dieyi and Xiaolou.
您一叫 他们立马就来 看您来啦
They came as soon as they heard you wanted to see them.
哎哟 这可怎么了不得了
Oh, this really is something!
师傅
Master!
是两位角儿来啦
The two famous actors are here!
徒弟该死
We are unworthy of you.
哎哟
Ah.
- 师父 - 我这面子天大了去啦
- Master, - You really have given me a lot of face.
哎
Ah.
我这怎么当得起
I'm deeply honoured.
啊 请坐 请坐
Please, have a seat.
受老朽一拜啊
Let this decrepit old man pay his respects.
徒弟不敢
Master, your students wouldn't presume...
不敢
Wouldn't presume!
而今 什么你们不敢
What wouldn't you presume?
程蝶衣
Cheng Dieyi,
当初 是你师哥把你 成全出来的
Cheng Dieyi, Xiaolou helped make you what you are today.
现在 你师哥不唱戏了
Now he's not singing anymore.
你也该拉他一把吧
It's time for you to give him a hand.
快着点啊
Come on!
给我动手啊
Do it!
小豆子
Little Douzi!
小石头
Little Shitou!
你们俩起小 这点故事
There's been a lot of water under the bridge
话说来长啦
since you were children.
怎么啊
Now,
现在成角儿了 谱大了
you're great actors. You're too big for your britches.
啊
Why?
就什么都忘了
But have you forgotten?
到了这个时候 就不忍心 啊
Don't you have the heart for it anymore?
你要喜欢就纵着他 不许护着他
Did I tell you to spoil and indulge him?
我叫你看着他
Did I tell you to sit by...
糟塌戏
while he wastes his talents?
诶 诶
Hey, hey.
我叫你看着他
Did I tell you to cover up for him?
- 我来 师傅 - 糟塌戏
- Master! - To desecrate the opera!
师傅
Master...
是我没出息
It's me who's the no-hoper.
您打我
Punish me!
老爷子
Listen to me, Grandpa,
您猜怎么着
can you guess what I have to say?
现而今 小楼可是我的人了
Xiaolou belongs to me these days,
您打他也成
If you want to hit him,
您得先告我一声呀
If you want to hit him, you've got to notify me first.
菊仙
Juxian!
哟
Oh,
您是花满楼那姑娘不是
It's that girl from the House of Blossoms, isn't it?
唉哟 您今儿个可是第一位贵客
Today, you are our number one guest.
您可得坐好
Make yourself comfortable.
喝好啊 看好了再去
Have a drink and a look around.
您请
Please!
- 我叫你吃喝嫖赌  - 打得好
- Did I teach you to eat, drink, - Good! I deserve it!
- 我叫你玩蛐蛐  - 打得好
- go whoring and gamble? Play with crickets? - Good! I deserve it!
我叫你当行头
Did I teach you to pawn your costumes?
师傅保重
Master take care!
- 我叫你糟塌戏  - 打得好
- To desecrate the opera! - Good! I deserve it!
哎呀 打得好
Good! I deserve it!
诶 打得好
慢着
Hold on!
这当师哥的糟塌戏
If he's desecrating the opera,
您活该打他
you ought to punish him.
可这当师弟的这个
But don't you figure his stage brother...
请问您 这算什么
...has a gesture in it as well?
菊仙
Juxian!
我既是花满楼的
I'm from the House of Blossoms.
自然不归 你们喜福成科班的管
This is none of my business,
可是您这当师傅的
but as their teacher,
也不能只听一面之词不是
shouldn't you listen to both sides of the story?
闭嘴
Shut up!
老爷们儿的事 没你说话的份儿
This is between us men! Keep out of it!
段小楼
Duan Xiaolou,
你可真知道疼人啦
you really are a tender soul!
再打呀
Hit me again!
你再胡唚
If you don't shut up,
我他妈打死你
I'll kill you.
- 诶 别 别介… - 别拦着我
- Don't! - Don't stop me!
好啊
Good.
今儿个 你打死我 算你赚了一个
Do that. You'll take two lives at once.
让你老段家 断子绝孙去吧
The Duan family line will stop with you!
诶
Why?
谁让你们俩 站起来的
Who told you to stand up?
哼 嘿 嘿
Heh heh heh.
小石头
Shitou,
听见了没有啊
are you paying attention?
啊
Ah,
你也是个快当爹的人了
You're going to be a father.
这么瞎混下去 丢了玩艺儿
If you keep wasting your time and lose your skills,
你以后 你拿什么请我 喝满月酒啊
how are you going to afford a celebration banquet for the birth?
跪近点
Kneel closer to one another!
再靠紧着点儿
Closer!
好好练 好好练
Work harder!
都拿稳了
Get a good grip!
腿伸直了 给我绷直了
Stretch those legs! Stretch!
仰起头
Raise your head.
慢着 慢着
Wait a minute!
你练的这是"夜奔"
You're practising "Fleeing by Night," aren't you?
扮的是林冲
You're playing Lin Chong.
林冲什么人呐
Who's this Lin Chong?
那是八十万禁军教头
He's head of the palace guard,
不是小毛贼
not some sneaky little thief.
拿着
Take this.
都瞧我的
Attention everyone!
看看什么是 盖世英雄
This is what a great hero's like.
“丈夫有泪不轻弹”
A man doesn't lightly shed hi tears...
“只因未到伤心处”
Unless his heart has broken.
别动
Don't!
师傅罚我七天都跪
The teacher told me to kneel for seven days as punishment,
还没到日子呢
time's not up yet!
科班都散了
The troupe has disbanded...
你还傻跪什么呀
What's the point of this idiotic kneeling?
师傅说了 要想成角儿
Master said that only you have the power...
就得自个儿 成全自个儿
...to make yourself a great actor.
旁人都走了
Everyone else has left.
你也家去吧
You ought to go home too.
我打小被捡回来的
I was found on the street as a baby.
没家
I've got no other home.
没告诉谁捡的你
Do you know who found you?
没告诉
No!
说怕我知道了是谁
They said if I knew I'd get a big head...
犯狂 不用功
...and wouldn't work hard.
还想唱戏吗
Do you still want to sing opera?
唱 要饭也唱 要成角儿
Yes, even if I have to beg to support myself!
你叫什么
What's your name?
小四
Xiao Si.
“只听得众兵丁们议论”
I hear the talk of the soldiers
四儿 你下去跟经理说 别闹出事来
Xiao Si, go tell the manager to avoid trouble.
诶
Yes.
“口声声露出了离散之心”
And it is all about running away
嘿 怎么不唱了
What's this? Why aren't you singing?
别乱
Don't make trouble!
诶诶 小楼 去不得啊
Don't go, Xiaolou.
诶 快去追啊
It's not worth it!
各位老总
Soldiers! Gentlemen!
这戏园子里头
You can't just wave your...
没有用手电筒 晃人的规矩
...flashlights around in the theatre.
连日本人 也没那么闹过
Even the Japanese didn't do this sort of thing.
大伙儿都是来听戏的
Everyone's here for the opera.
请回座上去吧
Please return to your seats.
说得好
All right.
回去
Seats, everyone!
可是有一样
But...
替日本人叫好 成不成
can we let him get away with speaking up for the Japanese?
不成
No!
打
Get him!
我操你大爷
Fuck your mother!
小楼
Xiaolou!
你放开他
Leave him alone!
你放开他 放开他
放开
Leave him alone!
喂 菊仙
Juxian!
快...快
Hurry!
有我在这儿
I'm here,
菊仙
Juxian...
快 快 凳子…
Get her a stool. Hurry!
您瞧 段太太呢
Mrs Duan has to get to hospital.
- 赶紧送医院 先保住大人再说 - 好
- Save her first and worry about the baby later. - Right.
赶紧着呀
Hurry!
让开
Let us through!
诶呦嚯 嘿
Hey, hey, hey
瞧不就是公共治安 这么大点事吗
There was only a minor disturbance.
还至于 至于劳动诸位 弄出这么大的动静
Such a show of force, is it really necessary?
要动罚款
To be fined.
噢 罚款
You can fine us.
还要抓人呐
Why do you need to arrest anyone?
这戏园子砸了
The theatre's been trashed,
人也快打死了 你们还要抓人呐
people beaten, and you still want to arrest him?
可不 可不能够怪他
We can't blame him.
快把他放开
Let him go!
走
Move!
数他狠
He's ruthless
你直说
You speak up!
这点钱 嘿嘿 辛苦了
This money... Thank you!
你们凭什么抓人
Why?
凭什么
What for?
程蝶衣犯的是汉奸罪
Cheng Dieyi betrayed the country to the Japanese.
走
Move it!
你们凭什么 说他是汉奸
How can you say that about him?
师傅
Teacher,
你凭什么说他是汉奸
How can you say that about him?
段老板
Mr Duan!
Mr Duan,
孩子怕是保不住了
I'm afraid she's lost the baby.
小楼
Xiaolou,
我真对不住你
I'm so sorry.
你忙你的去
Go do what you have to do.
你这师弟呀
I don't know whether...
也不知道这世道 跟他找别扭呢
...Dieyi goes looking for trouble...
还是他跟这个世道 找别扭
...or if it's trouble that comes looking for him.
总是轻省不了
But there seems no avoiding it.
早晚还得出乱子
Sooner or later, he'll come to grief.
只要你跟他在一起
Whenever you're with him,
我这心里 就不踏实
my heart's in my throat.
咱们的孩子没了
Now I've lost our child,
我可就剩你一人了
you're all I have left.
往后跟你一起去要饭 我都没二话
I don't care if I have to beg with you on the streets,
可就有一样
all I ask...
小楼
Xiaolou,
你得让我这心里 太太平平的
all I ask is peace of mind.
你把他救出来了
If you help him now,
咱们可就不欠他的了
we'll no longer owe him anything.
往后你别跟他唱了
Don't perform with him anymore.
你答应我
Promise me this.
你得给我立字据呀
Put it in writing.
啊
Ok?
四爷
Master Yuan,
蝶衣这条性命
Dieyi's life...
可就全仰仗您啦
...in your hands.
这点 您先打点着
Count this.
但凡不够 咱们回头再… 是吧
If it's not enough...
- 啊 - 诶 诶 哼
- Oh. - Yes.
袁四爷
Master Yuan,
您只要是救出蝶衣
If only you'll save Dieyi,
我们哥俩三年的包银 全归了您
we'll give you all our earnings for the next three years.
哼
Hum.
没你们的包银 你当我就喂不起这几只鸟啊
You think I need your money to keep my birds from starving?
这位是
And this gentleman is...?
这不小楼吗
Don't you recognise Xiaolou?
那什么
What's that,
给蝶衣唱霸王 那段小楼啊
He plays the king to Dieyi's concubine.
那该他救虞姬去呀
Then it should be he who saves Concubine Yu!
呀 我的亲老爷子呐 那不是戏吗
My dear man, that's only a play!
可着全北平
All Peiping knows that...
谁不知道袁四爷 才是梨园行的真霸王呀
...Master Yuan is the true king of the theatre!
是吗
Is that so?
噢 是 是
It's true.
是
诶 这说到戏 我倒要请教段老板
Speaking of theatre, I'd like to ask Mr Duan something.
这霸王回营亮过相 去见这虞姬
When the king returns to see Concubine Yu...
到底该走几步啊
How many steps should he take?
七步
Seven.
走我瞧瞧
Show me.
走我瞧瞧呀
Come on, show me!
四爷
Master Yuan...
诶 这是什么 什么 干吗啊
What is this for?  What are you doing?
这是袁四爷的府上吧
Is this the honourable home of Master Yuan?
有位叫程蝶衣的
When a man called Cheng Dieyi...
让人逮走的时候 说是
was arrested, he said...
这把剑的主人能救他
the owner of this sword would be able to rescue him.
您瞅瞅
Have a look,
认得吗
Do you recognise it?
瞧您这意思
From your expression,
我是找对主儿了
I see I've come to the right place.
那成
Good.
这剑呐 我给您搁这儿啦
I'll put the sword here.
啊
Oh.
这剑找着主儿 我也就放心了
I'm so relieved to have found its owner.
可这人哪 也总有指望错的时候
But sometimes one's hopes are misplaced.
袁四爷
Master Yuan,
您可别怪罪蝶衣呀
you mustn't blame Dieyi.
诶 弄明白啰
Hey, I see.
他给日本人唱堂会
He didn't say I...
怕不是袁…
I put him up to it,
袁某的指使吧
did he?
哟
Oh,
要是您袁四爷 让他去的
If you were involved,
他能让人给逮起来吗
he wouldn't be in trouble, would he?
那是
True!
诶
Oh dear!
一屋的记者 都在家里等着呢
There's a roomful of reporters waiting at home.
- 小楼 那爷 - 诶
- Xiaolou, Mr Na, - Ok.
咱们走
Xiaolou, Mr Na, let's go.
- 诶 别 别 慢着 话说清楚啰 - 那爷
- Wait a moment! Let's talk. -  Mr Na.
袁四爷让我来关照你
Master Yuan asked me to talk to you.
赶明儿个上了法庭
Tomorrow in court,
你得说是日本人 拿枪逼着你 去唱的堂会
say the Japanese put a gun to your head.
在兵营里头 给你动了刑
Say they tortured you.
旁的 袁四爷都替你安排妥当了
Master Yuan has made arrangements for everything else.
这是小楼让我交给你的
This is from Xiaolou.
蝶衣 你别怨我们
Dieyi, don't be angry with us.
小楼的孩子
The death of...
死了
...Xiaolou's child...
这就是你们在一块儿唱戏的报应
was karmic retribution for your partnership.
出去以后
After you get out of here,
你走你的阳关道 去吧
just go your own way.
查伶人程蝶衣 在我中华民国 对日抗战时期
During the War of Resistance against the Japanese,
竟与日寇驻平警备旅团之敌酋 青木三郎
the accused, Cheng Dieyi, performed pornographic works
互通款曲 狼狈为奸
for the Japanese troops under Aoki Saburo.
以淫词艳曲 为日寇作堂会演出
Cheng and Aoki expressed mutual affection and acted in collusion,
长敌之气焰 灭我之尊严
boosting enemy morale and damaging national self-respect.
敌酋青木三郎 在日军投降后
After the Japanese surrender, Aoki refused to give up
仍有反抗举动 已被我军击毙
and was shot dead by our troops.
其与被告往来之罪证相片 已落入我方
His association with the accused is well documented in photographs.
现出示法庭 铁证如山
The evidence is ironclad.
传...
We call on...
证人 袁世卿
the witnesses Yuan Shiqing,
段小楼
Duan Xiaolou...
那坤 出庭
and Na Kun.
世卿世受国恩
The government has always been good to me.
岂敢昧法
I wouldn't dare deceive the court.
更不敢 当众违背天理良心
Nor would I betray the laws of heaven nor my own conscience.
程蝶衣 确实是被日本人 用手铐铐走的
Cheng Dieyi was taken away in handcuffs by the Japanese.
还用手枪顶其项背威胁
They put a gun to the back of his neck,
就是后脖梗子
is the back stalk.
段小楼
Duan Xiaolou!
啊 是 是
Uh, it's true.
日本人
The Japanese...
他是打了我师弟
...beat up my stage brother.
这四爷全说了
Exactly as Master Yuan has just described.
那坤
Na Kun!
诶 他们...
He...
他...人...
方才检查官声言
The procurator spoke...
程之所唱 为淫词艳曲
...of "pornographic" singing.
实为大谬
That's absurd.
程 当晚所唱
That evening, Cheng sang...
是昆曲“牡丹亭·游园”一折
...excerpts from "Peony Pavilion" and "Wandering in a Garden".
略有国学常识者 都明白
Anyone with a smidgen of traditional learning knows...
此折乃国剧文化中之最精粹
...they're opera classics.
何以在检查官先生口中
How can you call...
竟成了淫词艳曲了呢
...them pornographic?
如此糟践戏剧国粹
Given such an insult to our culture,
到底是谁...
we must ask who in fact...
专门辱我民族精神
is insulting our national spirit...
灭我国家尊严
...and dignity?
好…
Bravo!
被告人 程蝶衣
We ask the accused, Cheng Dieyi,
证人所述 属实吗
have the witnesses told the truth?
被告人
The court...
本庭 要求你对日本军部事件
...wishes to hear what the accused...
作自我陈述
...has to say.
程蝶衣
Cheng Dieyi!
堂会我去了
I sang for the Japanese.
我也恨日本人
I hate the Japanese too.
可是他们...
But they...
没有打我
...didn't lay a hand on me.
被告人程蝶衣
Cheng Dieyi...
你有义务和权利
you have the right and duty...
用事实来证明 你清白的人格
...to clear your name.
你 再仔细回忆一下
Reconsider carefully...
再做一次陈述
...and tell us again what happened.
青木要是活着
If Aoki lived,
京戏 就传到日本国去了
he'd have taken Peking Opera to Japan.
你们杀了我吧
Just kill me, why don't you?
四爷
Master Yuan,
你们怎么进来了
How did you people get in here?
四爷
Master Yuan,
诶 四爷 您不能走啊 四爷
Please, Master Yuan, don't leave.
我走不走 他都死定
What does it matter? He's as good as dead.
诶...四爷 四爷
Master Yuan,
您不能走
you can't go.
您走他就完了
If you go, he's finished for sure.
诶 四爷
Master Yuan,
本庭宣布
The court has made its decision.
程蝶衣汉奸一案
The case of the traitor Cheng Dieyi...
暂停审理
...is suspended.
被告程蝶衣 交保具结 予以释放
The accused is released under bond.
休庭
Court dismissed!
这怎么回事
What's going on?
程蝶衣
Cheng Dieyi,
你他妈耍我呀你
are you playing with me, goddamn it?
程蝶衣
Cheng Dieyi.
我等着
I'm waiting.
程老板
Goodbye...
回头见
Mr Cheng.
程先生 请
This way, Mr Cheng.
司令官 到...
The commander has arrived.
列...
Attention!
“春香”
Chunxiang!
“小姐”
Miss!
“不到园里 怎知春色如许”
How can one know spring colours, unless one visits the garden?
娘
Ma,
上信收到了吧
did you get my last letter?
儿在这儿 一切都好
Everything's fine here.
您不用挂念
Don't worry about me
我师哥小楼
My stage brother Xiaolou...
对我处处照应体贴
...looks after me with great kindness
我们白天 练功喊嗓
We rehearse by day...
晚上同台演戏
...and perform at niqht.
跟过去往常 一模一样
Just like before
外面世道 虽不大好
The world's not what It used to be,
不过我们 只求平安
but all we ask i a peaceful Iife
把戏唱完拿回包银 太太平平就是了
We sing and get paid for it, what more could you want?
这来福 就等着您 喷它两口香呐
Lucky the Cat wants you to blow some opium smoke at her.
瞧见没有
See that?
欢实了不是
It sure makes her come to life!
诶 蝶衣
Dieyi,
这信是寄到
should I mail this to...?
老地方
The usual address.
诶 得啦
Done.
这林黛玉 要是不焚稿
All you classic consumptive...
那叫什么林黛玉呀
...heroines burn your letters.
诶 你瞅没有
Have you seen this?
这玩艺儿 我给您淘回来了
I have bought this toy for you.
要不要
Do you want it?
不要
If you don't,
不要 我可撕啦啊
If you don't, I'll tear it up.
对 我真撕了啊
I'll tear it up.
撕了
Do it!
撕啰 诶哟 撕啰
I'll do it!
四儿
Xiao Si!
段师傅收下了
Master Duan has taken the sword.
诶嘿哟 我这水流千遭 到了还得归海不是
The river's course is twisted, but in the end it flows to the sea!
虞姬跟霸王说话 中间还得隔条乌江啊
But what gulf still lies between our concubine and our king?
赶紧的 不然 刘邦可就杀进城来了
Talk to each other already. Liu Bang's about to enter the city!
我们旗人 好歹还坐了 三百年天下
For better or worse, we Manchus ruled for three centuries.
这民国才几年呀 这是
The Republic's only just begun,
说话 人家就兵临城下了
and already it's being overthrown!
共产党来了 也得听戏不是
But even the Communists have to have opera.
这新君临朝 江山易主
The empire may change hands,
庆典 能少得了您二位吗
but you'll still get top billing at the celebrations for the new dynasty!
不能够
You can bet your life on it!
咱们就等着点新票子吧
We're just waiting to see what their money looks like!
怎么着 还敢打人家伤兵不敢呐
Well, do you still want to fight their ragtag troops?
他们别瞎闹
They'd better behave themselves.
闹哄急了 照打
Otherwise, I'll still fight them.
诶 别呀
Hey, Don't.
您要有袁四爷那谱 那行
If you had Master Yuan's class, you'd prosper
甭管哪朝哪代 人家永远是爷
no matter who was in power.
咱们不可行 那不一样
It's not the same for us!
还认得我吗
Do you recognise me?
抽盒
Cigarettes! Buy one!
张公公
Mr Zhang...
不认得我们了
don't you know us?
抽盒
Buy a pack!
“大王慷慨悲歌”
The king's sad song,
“令人泪下”
moves one to tears.
“待妾妃歌舞一回”
Let me dance and sing for you,
“聊以解忧如何”
and talk away your sorrow
“有劳妃子”
You do so much for me
“如此妾妃”
I'd...
“献...”
...do...
“献丑了”
...do anything...for you
四儿
Xiao Si,
要什么 给人什么
give them whatever they want.
可千万别动手
Don't resist.
诶
Yes.
各位老总
Soldiers, gentlemen.
实在是对不住
I'm terribly sorry...
我们这位角儿 今儿个
Tonight, he just...
“向前 向前 向前”
Advance, advance, advance!
预备 唱
Prepare to sing!
“向前 向前 向前”
Advance, advance, advance!
“我们的队伍向太阳”
We are marching toward the sun
“脚踏着祖国的大地”
Through this great motherland of ours
“背负着民族的希望”
We carry the hopes of a nation on our backs
“我们是一支不可战胜的力量”
We are an unbeatable force!
程老板
Mr Cheng,
您熬不住
if you can't take it,
您 您就再抽一口得了
if you can't take it, have another smoke.
四儿 快去叫段老板去
Xiao Si, go call Mr Duan.
“打倒反动戏霸袁世卿”
Down with the counter-revolutionary Yuan Shiqing!
“袁世卿与人民为敌 死路一条”
Yuan Shiqing has made the people his enemy. Death to him!
“提高警惕”
Raise your level of vigilance!
袁爷
Master Yuan.
“擦亮眼睛”
Raise your level of vigilance!
综上所述
To sum up,
反革命分子袁世卿
the counter-revolutionary Yuan Shiqing
一贯反共反人民
has always opposed the Communist Party and the people.
危害一方 罪恶滔天
He has harmed his community and is guilty of monstrous crimes.
不杀 不足以平民愤
Only execution can satisfy the people's anger!
“打倒反革命分子袁世卿”
Down with the counter-revolutionary Yuan Shiqing!
“打倒反动戏霸袁世卿”
Down with the tyrant of the opera world Yuan Shiqing!
“袁世卿死路一条”
Death to Yuan Shiqing!
“枪毙袁世卿”
Execute Yuan Shiqing!
押下去
Take him away!
消灭袁世卿
Eliminate Yuan Shiqing!
袁世卿 你还我的丈夫
Yuan Shiqing, you return my husband!
袁世卿 你也有今天啦
Yuan Shiqing, you have today too!
不杀 不足以平民愤
Only execution can satisfy the people's anger?
毙啦
Just like that?
就这么 把袁四爷毙啦
They're going to kill Master Yuan?
哎 你小声点
Keep your voice down.
“解放区的天 是明朗的天”
The sky of the liberated areas is clear and blue
“解放区的人民好喜欢”
The people of the liberated areas are happy
“民主政府爱人民”
The democratic government loves the people
“共产党的恩情说不完”
You can never say enough about the Party's loving kindness!
放开我 你放开我
Let me go! Release me!
我操你大爷
Fuck you!
操你大爷啊
别闹
Stop carrying on!
听着
Listening!
你听着
You listen!
再忍忍就过去了 听见没有
Are you listening? You'll get over it with time.
好了 别闹了
Good, calm down.
再忍忍 就过去了
Everything will be OK.
我操你大爷
Fuck you!
别闹了
Cut it out!
再闹 我就打你了
Cut it out or I'll hit you!
- 给我 - 别闹了
- Give it to me. - No kidding,
放开我
let me go!
不要动
Don't move!
怎么着
How is he?
看样子 得用点药
I think we'll have to give him some drugs.
你看着点
Keep an eye on him.
别让他挣蹦出来
Don't let him hurt himself.
诶 小楼 你可别走啊
Don't go, Xiaolou.
无碍的 他要想把大烟戒了
If he really wants to overcome his addiction to opium,
还得脱几层皮呢 这才是个头
he's going to have to go through hell! This is just the start.
诶
Hey.
我冷
I'm cold!
娘
Ma!
水都冻冰了
The water's all turned to ice!
我冷
I'm cold!
娘
Ma!
水都冻冰了
The water's all turned to ice!
我冷
I'm cold...
好了 好了
It's OK. Everything's all right.
“解放军的天是晴明的天”
The sky of the liberated areas is clear and blue
“解放区的人民好喜欢”
The people of the liberated areas are happy...
段师母
Mrs Duan!
你到哪儿去了
Where were you?
开会去了
A meeting.
A meeting?
诶
Yes.
小楼 师兄师弟们都来了
Xiaolou, the whole troupe's come.
诶 快请进
Come on in. Quick!
进来 进来啊
Come in! Come in!
换行头了啊
Ah, a costume change!
诶 多谢大伙来看我
Thank you all for coming to see me.
没事了 我好了
I'm fine now.
说得轻巧
Sounds easy now.
没见遭罪的时候呢
You didn't see him suffer!
蝶衣 起来吧
Dieyi,
起来吧
get out of bed.
全北京的大街小巷 都支愣着耳朵
All of Peking is waiting with bated breath
等着听霸王和虞姬出场呐
for the next appearance of the king and his Concubine!
什么叫“盛代元音”呐 这他妈就是
It'll be the goddamn golden hit of a golden era.
大家让我说几句
You've asked me to say a few words.
那我就说几句 说不好
I'm not sure how to put it.
现代戏
I think these modern operas...
有意思
...are interesting,
可现代戏的服装
but the costumes...
有点怪
...aren't very attractive.
不如行头好看
The backdrops are also too realistic,
布景也太实
nothing pleasures the eye.
京戏讲究的 是个情境
Yet Peking Opera puts great value on ambience.
唱 念 做 打
Song, recital, movement and acrobatics...
都在这个情境里面
...are part of this ambience.
穿上这一身 往布景前头一站
But if you're wearing outfits like these and standing...
玩艺再好 也不对头了
...in front of those backdrops, it just doesn't work.
我就怕 这么弄 就不是京戏了
I fear that this will be the end of opera, as we know it.
你们说呢
What do all of you think?
怎么现代戏
Are you saying that modern operas...
就不是京戏了
...aren't Peking Opera?
京戏是什么
What is Peking Opera after all?
就是八个字
You can put it succinctly.
无声不歌
No sound but is a song,
无动不舞
no movement but is a dance.
得好看 美
It must have beauty.
比方说啊
For instance...
- 这个... - 师傅
- This... - Teacher,
我没听明白
I don't get it.
等你流上 三船五车的汗
Practise. When you've sweated enough to fill buckets,
就明白了
you'll get it.
我还是不明白
I still don't understand.
四儿
Xiao Si!
我就是不明白
I just don't get it.
为什么古时候的英雄美人上了台
When ancient heroes and beauties take the stage,
就是京戏
why should it be Peking Opera?
现在劳动人民上了台 就不是京戏了
but not when the labouring masses do?
你这...说的是两码事
You're talking apples and pears.
- 放肆  - 你什么态度
- Upstart! - What's this attitude?
段师傅
Teacher Duan,
您说说
I'd like to hear from you.
小楼
Xiaolou!
外边要下雨了
It's raining.
给你伞
I've brought your umbrella.
接着
Catch!
得
Yes,
知道了
yes,
家去吧
run along home now.
一提这论理的事儿 我头就大
Discussions about ethics give me a headache.
依我看啊
I say...
只要是唱这西皮二黄
if it uses the traditional musical forms,
它就是京戏
then it's Peking Opera.
是不是
Am I right?
小楼
Xiaolou.
我...我发两句言 啊
I'd like to say something.
自打把这戏院 啊 交给咱们国家
I've been part of the New Society since giving...
咱就都是新人了
...my theatre to the state.
程同志 也不对
Comrade Cheng, I believe you're wrong.
这现代戏 它是个新事
Modern opera is a new venture,
咱们应当拥护啊 应当支持啊
it deserves our support.
功也不练 嗓也不吊
You never practise.
耍贫顶嘴 你倒学成了
If opera relied on being a smartass, you'd graduate with honours.
唱戏的不靠这个
Opera requires practice,
凭的是功夫 本事 玩艺儿
skill and talent.
没你的近道儿可走
There are no shortcuts!
罚我跪
By forcing me to kneel,
你犯法
you're breaking the law.
不罚 不罚你永远是下三滥
And if I don't punish you, you'll always be third-rate.
还想成角儿
You want to be a great actor?
做梦
Dream on!
没错 你领我来 哪儿是想让我成角儿
And when did you ever seriously want me to succeed?
你是想找个小力笨儿
All you've ever wanted is a coolie,
小催帮儿
a stage hand...
小跟包 小腿子 小龙套
a follower, a dogsbody, a bit player!
你放肆 你大胆
How dare you!
我让你胡说八道
You're speaking absolute rubbish!
胡说八道 胡说八道
还不给我跪下
Kneel down!
师傅
Master,
永没那日子啦
You won't live to see the day!
四儿
Xiao Si!
滚吧
Piss off then!
一辈子跑你的龙套去吧
Be a bit player your whole life!
程老板
Mr Cheng...
您这话要搁在旧社会说
I can hardly...
我信
...believe this...
在新社会说 我不信
It's like something out of the Old Society!
我要是再跑龙套
If I continue to get bit parts,
对不起您的栽培
I'll be unworthy of your patronage!
这么说
So,
你知道
you know?
啊
What?
啊 嘿嘿
Yes. Uh.
这 我这
Uh, I...
诶 我也是刚刚才知道
Uh, I just learned myself...
不对吧
That's not true,
段师傅
Teacher Duan.
昨儿开会 您可是在场的啊
You were there at the meeting last night.
你说的 你去通知 蝶衣换角儿嘛
But you said you'd notify Dieyi that you were replacing him.
啊
Ah.
可后来我觉着
I had second thoughts.
这话 您说最合适
I decided you should tell him.
您同意了嘛
Don't you agree?
这话您都不说
If you couldn't tell him,
还有谁能说呀
who could?
掭了
Take it off!
赶快唱啦 师哥 您别这样
Don't. Don't be like that!
师哥
Bro.
我他妈的不唱了
I won't fucking sing anymore!
谁爱唱 谁唱去
Let whoever wants to perform do so.
赶快唱啦 师哥 您别走
Don't. Don't be like that!
小楼
Xiaolou,
小楼 你不能走
Xiaolou, you mustn't go.
段小楼同志
Comrade Duan,
而今台下坐的 可都是劳动人民
that audience is made up of the Iabou ring masses.
唱不唱 您自个儿掂量着
You decide for yourself whether or not to sing for them.
小楼 虞姬都上了
Xiaolou, the concubine's on stage.
你该盯场了
You'd better hurry.
小楼
Xiaolou...
段老板
Mr Duan!
“自从我随大王东征西战”
I've followed my king on his military campaigns
“受风霜与劳碌年复年年”
Enduring the wind and frost, and hard toil year after year
“恨只恨”
I hate only the lawless tyrant,
“无道秦把生灵涂炭”
who has plunged our people, into an abyss of misery!
“只害得众百姓困苦颠连”
The people have suffered untold hardship and pain
“大王回营啊”
The king has returned to camp!
“来也”
I'm here
“大王”
My king!
“此一番连累你 多受惊慌”
I've caused you so much grief
多谢菊仙小姐
Thank you very much, Miss Juxian.
蝶衣
Dieyi!
蝶衣 你开开门
Dieyi, open the door! Open up!
蝶衣
Dieyi!
师哥给你赔不是 还不成吗
Won't you accept my apology?
那条小蛇 可是你把它捂活的
That little snake you rescued...
而今人家 已然修练成龙啦
...has turned into a veritable dragon!
不顺着他
You have to go along with it!
不顺着他 能成吗
You have to go along with it! What else can you do?
这戏总得唱吧 这可是你说的
No matter what, as you told me, you have to keep on singing!
你也不出来看看
Come on out and see what's playing...
这世上的戏 都唱到哪一出了
...in the theatre of life these days.
小豆子
Douzi,
你就听师哥一句
listen to your stage brother.
服个软
Go with the times!
那还不是我的霸王 你的虞姬呀
I'll still be the king and you my concubine!
虞姬 为什么要死
Why does the concubine have to die?
蝶衣啊
Dieyi,
你可真是不疯魔 不成活呀
Dieyi, why are you so impossible?
可那是戏
That's the play, for heaven's sake.
“中央人民广播电台”
Central People's Radio will now broadcast
“现在播送中国共产党中央委员会”
the decision of the Chinese Communist Party Central Committee
“关于无产阶级文化大革命的决定”
regarding the Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution,
“1966年8月8日通过”
passed on 8th August 1966.
“一”
First,
“社会主义革命的新阶段”
This new stage in socialist revolution
“当前开展的无产阶级文化大革命”
is an event that will touch
“是一场触及人们灵魂的大革命”
the very soul of the people!
“敢想 敢说”
A good Communist mustbe brave...
“敢做 敢闯 敢革命”
speak righteously andfight for the revolution
“一句话 敢造反”
The greatest virtue fora revolutionary soldier...
“这是无产阶级革命家 最基本 最可贵的品质”
is to overthrow the reactionary powers
“是无产阶级党性的基本原则”
This is the foundation ofourrevolutionarystruggle
“不造反 就是百分之一百的修正主义”
If asoldier does not do this, he is nota true revolutionary
“修正主义统治学校十七年了”
Those who oppose the revolution...
“现在不反 更待何时”
willbesent to reform school to adjust theirattitudes
“有些大胆的反对造反的人”
There they will find...
“今天突然变得忸怩起来”
...their anti-revolutionary stance will diminish
“絮絮叨叨 吞吞吐吐”
There are those who repeatedly complain...
“什么太片面了呀”
that revolution is not appropriate.
“什么太狂妄了呀”
That it's too violent...
“什么太粗暴了呀”
that it's too aggressive...
“什么太过分了呀”
that it's too abrupt for thepeople
“这统统是谬论”
All of thatis ridiculous
干嘛 怎么想起喝酒来了
What are you doing? Drinking at a time like this?
想喝一口
feel like it.
“我们既然要造反 就由不得你们了”
Since we are going to revolt, we can't help you!
反正这两杯子
Anyway, jade cups...
也沾上“四旧”了
...were part of the "Old Society".
留不住了
We can't keep them.
不如用上一回
Might as well use them a last time.
来
Come on!
还不碎
It still won't break!
我怕
I'm so afraid!
我梦见 我站在一个大高楼上
I dreamed I was on top of a tall building alone,
四外都是白云
amongst the clouds.
我就是想往下跳
I wanted to jump.
我想往下跳
你跳呀
Jump!
我在那儿呢
I'd catch you.
你不在那儿
You weren't there.
啊 小楼
Xiaolou,
你不会不要我了吧
you wouldn't leave me, would you?
小楼
Xiaolou,
这把剑 从哪儿来的
Where did this sword come from?
是…程蝶衣送给我的
Cheng Dieyi gave it to me.
送过你几次
How many times did he give it to you?
两次啊
Twice.
第二次 是什么时候
When was the second time?
北京...快解放的时候
Shortly before the liberation of Peking.
在哪儿
Where?
在…
On...
在戏园子大街
On... the street in front of the theatre.
当时 你说过什么话没有
What did you say to each other?
当时挺乱的
It was quite chaotic,
我记不得了
I don't remember.
你再想想
Think about it.
没有什么呀
We didn't say anything!
好好想想
Keep thinking.
没有 想不起来了
If we did, I can't recall.
你说过要对共产党
Something about what...
怎么怎么样的话没有
...you'd do to the Communists?
啊
What?
没有
No!
肯定没有 绝对没有
Certainly not!
要有 杀了我也不冤
I'd stake my life on it.
要有人证明你说过呢
But what if we've got a witness?
谁
Who?
王八蛋 让他出来
Bring out the bastard!
老那
Na Kun!
我
I...
我说什么了
What did I say?
要不然 我给您提个醒
I'll give you a hint.
还敢惹人家伤兵不敢呐
Something about ragtag troops.
那坤
Na Kun!
你血口喷人
This is pure slander!
你这个反动戏园子老板
You reactionary old theatre boss!
你…你光想保你自己 那坤
You only want to protect yourself.
你说共产党来了 你也照打不误
You said you'd take on their ragtag troops.
没 没 没有
No!
我没说
No! I never said that!
我…我当…我当时的意思是
What I meant was...
我当时是说
What I said was...
不 没有 我们什么也没说
No, I said nothing at all!
那爷 那爷
Mr Na, Mr Na,
您...那爷 您得替我…那爷
Mr Na, Mr Na, help me... Mr Na!
段小楼
Duan Xiaolou,
你不是从小就拍砖吗
you've been smashing bricks since you were a boy, yes?
拍给我瞧瞧
Do one for us.
拍呀
Do it!
Come on!
段小楼
Duan Xiaolou,
你是霸王吗
aren't you the "king"?
不 不是
No, I'm not.
你不是一直是霸王吗
But you've always been the "king", haven't you?
那都是戏
That's just an opera.
不是真的
it's not real life.
旧社会 你去过妓院吧
Did you go to brothels in the Old Society?
去过
Yes.
你不觉得可耻吗
Don't you think that's shameful?
我觉得 可耻
Yes.
你娶菊仙的时候 她是什么身份
When you married Juxian, what was she?
妓女
A prostitute.
好
Good.
你要好好揭发程蝶衣
Now tell us what we need to know about Cheng Dieyi.
当然
Of course,
你也可以不揭发
you don't have to tell us anything.
袁世卿的下场 你是亲眼看见的
You saw what happened to Yuan Shiqing.
你自己决定吧
Make your own decision.
“横扫一切牛鬼蛇神”
Sweep away all cow demons and snake spirits!
“敌人不投降 就将他灭亡”
If the enemy doesn't surrender, we will destroy him!
“揪出黑帮 斩断黑手”
Uncover the Black Gangs! Cut off the Black Hands!
“揪出伸进文艺界的黑手”
Seize the Black Hands that have infiltrated the cultural world!
“革命无罪 造反有理”
Revolution is no crime, rebellion is justified!
“横扫一切牛鬼蛇神”
Sweep away all cow demons and snake spifrits!
小楼
Xiaolou!
打倒段小楼
Down with Duan Xiaolou!
段小楼是反动霸王
Duan Xiaolou is the reactionary king!
段小楼 段小楼不老实
Duan Xiaolou isn't telling the truth!
段小楼 程蝶衣是黑线人物
Duan Xiaolou and Cheng Dieyi are anti-Party elements!
打倒程蝶衣
Down with Cheng Dieyi!
打倒段小楼
Down with Duan Xiaolou!
说呀
Talk!
说
“横扫一切牛鬼蛇神”
Obliterate all class enemies!
说
Talk!
我说
All right. I'll tell you.
他是个戏痴 戏迷 戏疯子
He's totally mad about opera, obsessed!
谁
Who?
说清楚
Make yourself clear.
说 说…
Come on!
程蝶衣
Cheng Dieyi!
他是只管唱戏的 啊
All he cares about is opera...
他不管台下 坐的什么人
No matter who was in the audience,
什么阶级
which class they belonged to,
他都卖力的唱 他玩命的唱
he'd still give it his all.
- 避重就轻 - 没有 没有
- Stop avoiding the real issues. - No...
你不老实
You're not being straight with us!
“段小楼不投降 就叫他灭亡”
If you don't give in, we will annihilate you.
抗日…抗日战争刚刚开始
At the start of the War of Resistance,
他...他就给日本侵略者唱堂会
he sang for the Japanese.
他
He...
他就
He was...
他就当了汉奸
He was a... traitor!
“打倒程蝶衣”
Down with Cheng Dieyi!
- 蝶衣 - “打倒程蝶衣”
- Cheng Dieyi! - Down with Cheng Dieyi!
他 给国民党伤兵唱戏
He sang for wounded KMT soldiers,
给北平行辕的反动头子唱戏
for reactionary theatre bosses.
给资本家唱
He sang for capitalists,
给地主老财唱 给太太小姐唱
landlords, the idle rich, their wives and daughters.
给地痞流氓唱 给宪兵警察唱
He sang for hooligans. He sang for soldiers and policemen.
他 给大戏霸袁世卿唱
He sang for the tyrant of the opera world, Yuan Shiqing!
“打倒程蝶衣”
Down with Cheng Dieyi!
再说 还有呢
What else? Tell us.
说 说
Talk!
他抽大烟
He smoked opium.
他抽起大烟来没命
He smoked opium like there was no tomorrow.
不知抽光了多少人 劳动人民的血和汗
He smoked away the blood and sweat of the labouring masses.
揭 揭实质问题
Keep going. Get to the point.
再说会儿好
Speak!
说 说
Go on!
“打倒程蝶衣”
Down with Cheng Dieyi!
说 说
Talk!
不要打他 小楼
Don't hit him! Xiaolou!
说
Talk!
他为了讨好 大戏霸袁世卿
In order to get on Yuan Shiqing's good side...
他
he...
你有没有
did you or did you not?
他
He...
他给袁世卿
He became Yuan Shiqing's...
他当了…当了…
his...
小楼
Xiaolou!
他当了
his...
你有没有… 你当了…
Did you...? Did you...?
你当 你当 当 当…
You were...were...his...
“横扫一切牛鬼蛇神”
Sweep away all cow demons and snake spirits!
“打倒程蝶衣”
Down with Cheng Dieyi!
“打倒段小楼”
Down with Cheng Duan Xiaolou!
看什么你们 低头低头 都低头
Look at you guys, bow your head. All bow their heads.
“横扫一切牛鬼蛇神”
Cow demons and snake spirits.
你们都骗我
You've all betrayed me!
都骗我
Betrayed me!
我也揭发
I've got something to unmask as well!
揭发姹紫嫣红 揭发断壁残垣
I want to unmask splendiferous beauty and desolate ruin.
段…段小楼 你…
Duan Xiaolou, you've no conscience.
天良丧尽 狼心狗肺
You're as greedy as a wolf, cruel as a cur.
空剩一张人皮了
You're the shell of a man.
自打你贴上这个女人
From the moment you started hanging around with this woman,
我就知道完了
I knew you were finished.
什么都完了
Everything was finished!
你当今儿个是小人作乱 祸从天降
You think disaster just falls from the sky?
不是 不对
No.
是咱们自个儿 一步一步
We have come step by step towards this fate.
一步步走到这步田地来的 报应
It's retribution.
我早就不是东西了
I'm despicable, and have been so for a long time.
连你楚霸王 都跪下来求饶了
But now even the King Of Chu is on his knees begging for mercy!
嗯 那这京戏 它能不亡吗
Can Peking Opera survive this indignity?
能不亡吗
It's doomed, is it not?
报应
This is what's called retribution!
Karmic retribution!
我还要揭发
And I have something to unmask as well.
就是她
See that woman?
她是什么人
Who's she?
我来告诉你们 她是什么人
I'll tell you!
臭婊子
Slut!
淫妇
Pan Jinlian!
她是花满楼的头牌妓女 潘金莲
Top whore at the House of Blossoms!
你斗她 去斗她 斗她呀
Struggle against her!
斗 斗死她 斗死她 斗死她
Struggle her to death!
段小楼 她是不是妓女
Duan Xiaolou, is it true she was a prostitute?
是不是
Well, was she?
说啊
Tell us!
说
是
Yes... yes...!
你爱她吗
Do you love her?
嗯
What?
爱不爱
Do you?
不
No,
不爱 不爱她
No, I don't love her!
真的不爱
Is this the truth?
真的不爱 真的
Really. I don't love her.
我不 真的不爱她
我跟她划清界线
Really. I'll never have anything to do with her again.
“横扫一切牛鬼蛇神”
Sweep away all cow demons and snake spirits!
我从此跟她划清界线了
Nothing at all.
我跟她划清界线了
I'll never have anything to do with her again.
菊仙
Juxian!
“听奶奶 讲革命”
Liten to grandma talk of revolution
“英勇悲壮”
A tale of heroism and tragedy
“却原来 我是风里生来雨里长”
I was a child of the rain and wind...
“汉兵已略地”
The Han troops have taken the kingdom,
“四面楚歌声”
the songs of Chu can be heard on all sides!
“君王”
My king!
“大王 快将宝剑赐予妾身”
My king, quickly give me your precious sword
“妃子 不 不…不可寻此短见呐”
No, you mustn't take your life!
“大王 快将宝剑赐予妾身”
My king, quickly give me your precious sword
“千万不可”
No, you must not do this!
“大王 快将宝剑…”
"My king, quickly give me..."
不灵了 不灵了
It's no good.
不跟趟儿了
I can't hack it anymore.
诶 老了
I'm old.
“小尼姑 年方二八”
At sixteen lam a nun...
“正…正青春被师傅削去了头发”
My hair shorn at youth's prime
“我本是男儿郎”
I am by nature a boy
“又不是女娇娥”
Not a gril
错了 又错了
Wrong! You've done it again!
我本是男儿郎
I am by nature a boy,
又不是女娇娥
not a girl!
来 我们再来
Come on, let's try it again
“大王 快将宝剑赐予妾身”
My king, quickly give me your precious sword
“妃子 不 不…不可寻此短见呐”
No, you mustn't take your life!
“大王 快将宝剑赐予妾身”
My king, quickly give me your precious sword
“千万不可”
No, you must not do this!
“大王 快将宝剑赐予妾身”
Give me your sword
“千万不可”
No, never!
“大王 汉兵他…他…他杀进来了”
My king, the soldiers of Han... they've entered the city!
“在哪里”
Where?
蝶衣
Dieyi!
小豆子
Douzi!